[Music]
she's doing 11 kilos over the world
record a month out that is so far ahead
I love a friendly rivalry in
bodybuilding I love when the guys train
together and I think it brings a really
wholesome yet Competitive Edge to
everything it looks like Haley Adams
engine just never ends she could run
forever and never
stop welcome to strength weekly the
weekly YouTube show that keeps you up to
date on everything you need to know in
the barbell game we've already lapsed on
our New Year's resolutions but 2025 is
looking bright until then we're going to
bring you world records and a lot of
other stuff happening from around the
strength game this week including the
world of bodybuilding because a lot of
people debate whether that's a strength
sport or not we'll get into that I'm
sure at some point before I get into our
run of show Phillip Blackman I don't
know your middle name but that would
have sounded a lot better there should
folks subscribe to barbin on YouTube
before we proceed uh folks absolutely
should subscribe I'm subscribed you're
subscribed everybody who's Smart thin
intelligent wonderful handsome lovely
funny all of them were subscribed join
the join the crew Smart thin intelligent
handsome funny no no no no we're trying
to get wide as a house fil wide as a
house well also nice benefit everybody
who is jacked is subscribed so join the
crew thick is the new thin don't forget
that let's get to today's run of show
first up North Korean dominance so far
at the Asian weightlifting championship
and it's not even over they are coming
away with oodles and oodles of world
records and guess what they're not even
going to be competing at the Paris
Olympics because they haven't qualified
Haley Adams CrossFit Games Superstar
took last year off and has announced her
return to competition we're on American
soil we want to cheer for our Hometown
Heroes Amanda Lawrence 84 kgam
powerlifter multitime world record
holder Squat and big we're talking like
11 kilos over the world record in
training as she prepares for the
Sheffield we talk about why she might be
the American to watch especially on the
women's side for what is turning out to
be one of the biggest powerlifting
competitions of all time and finally
Chris Bumstead after a lot of Life
updates he's becoming a father he's back
to training after getting surgery a lot
of stuff going on here with Chris
Bumstead well he's back to training and
he has a fire lit under his butt talks
because that title he's got he might be
the first to admit it's in Jeopardy if
he doesn't Focus up we're going to get
into that Phil which of these red fire
hot stories are you most excited about
this week I'm actually really excited to
talk about North Korea because I it just
is going to loom over the Olympics
that this dominant Team all of a sudden
isn't going to be there but I'm also
very excited to shat about Haley Adam's
return to cross a 2024 season so let's
talk about North Korea the Asian
weightlifting championships are still
underway while we're recording this we
know that team China actually pulled out
of those we talked about that on a
previous broadcast the reason they gave
was that they wanted to give their
athletes more time to to Peak because
the Olympics are coming later this year
but even though team China is not
competing at the Asian weight listing
championships North Korea is still
showing how dominant they can be in
certain weight classes especially the
lighter weight classes on the women's
sides because they're coming away with
world records and they're beating
Chinese World Records or setting or
beating World standards Phil if you had
to come up with one word to describe
we'll go into specifics one word to
describe North Korea's performance so
far in the Asian weight championships
what would it be jarring jarring jarring
is good jarring I would say because I
think that everybody knew that they were
good but I don't think necessarily that
we were going to see best in the world
competing at China's level good yeah and
maybe even better because they're again
with China not competing North Korea is
doing the only thing they can do to show
that they could meet or even beat these
Chinese athletes in performance which is
to set new world records right reong gum
in the 49 kilogram category came with
two new world records one a cleaning
jerk of 125 kilos that's a 49 kilo woman
clean and jerking 125 kilos that's over
275 pounds just think about that cuz I
still am thinking about that and she
also set a new world record total with
220 kilos so 49s we've seen that be like
that's like like China's normally got
that a lock right and then she's coming
out and saying with this performance she
might be the best 49 kilo lifter in the
world we're not going to see her compete
later this year because they're not
going to be at the Paris Olympics just
as a reminder North Korea has not had
the number of requisite appearances at
Olympic qualifying events as a team to
qualify any athletes for the Paris
Olympics the iwf came out and clarified
North Korea will not be at the Paris
Olympics in weightlifting so we will not
see them there Phil a couple other
performances have really stood out from
these early sessions for the lighter
North Korean women any any off the top
of your mind wanan Sim I I hope I'm
pronouncing that correctly setting the
world record standards like achieving
those for the first time in the 45
kilogram class but we're we're seeing
these lifts from these uh North Korean
lifters that could challenge what China
is doing doing but we're not going to
see them compete directly and so once we
see China dominate at in Paris we're
going to be thinking oh when these two
countries meet on the world stage and
actually line their their athletes up in
these Cate in these weight categories
and go against each other live like that
is going to really be The Showdown of
okay who's the top team in the world now
and we have one other I mean we're only
a few sessions in sessions in between
when we record this and when it
publishes there might be more North
Korean World Records Kang hang gong I'm
probably butchering that set a new
snatch world record in the women's 55
kilo category five World Records across
three weight classes for the women heck
of a start to the competition until you
bring up a great point china is going to
be at the Paris Olympics North Korea is
not going to be at the Paris Olympics we
see China really dominating these
lighter women's weight classes we see
North Korea coming in and making a
statement that they can take these world
records and exceed Chinese totals on the
platform even though they're not
competing head-to-head it sets it up to
be the biggest what if of the 2024 Paris
Olympics and weightlifting it hearkens
back to those days in uh like the 90s
2000s when the Bulgarian team actually
was banned for doping Bulgaria was not
able to send athletes to compete under
their country's flag in weightlifting
yet at the same time they still had some
of the best weightlifters in the world
right so we do have these whifs
throughout the history of weightlifting
and I think the 20124 Paris Olympics and
North Korea not being there in
weightlifting is the most recent and
maybe one of the most Salient wha ifs in
the history of weightlifting at the
Olympics just my opinion yeah I think
it's going to it will add a an
additional layer of paint to the
coverage for the Olympic Games that
assuming that China continues to
dominance like they have over the last
several Olympic I mean uncountable
number of Olympics at this point
alongside that though is going to be
well the North Koreans were like at the
same numbers also breaking World Records
like if they were here would would the
metal count be the same you know like it
the coverage is going to have that
looming over it which isn't to say that
like it's not going to be credible
obviously it'll still be great but it is
going to set up for this inevitable
clash between these two Titans now in
the sport that I personally now very
excited to see after this performance by
North Korea uh leading into in an
Olympic Games year yeah for the next
quad you know for the for the quad
leading into the quad being the fouryear
period leading into the Los Angeles
Olympics um and again there are
complications there because North Korea
dprk they will sometimes compete on
American soil and they will sometimes
not compete on American soil right so
will we see them in Los Angeles it's
probably way too early to tell honestly
but I am personally excited for the next
time internationally we see China and
the dprk go head-to-head I think it is
going to be a fantastic series of
matches on the platform we've waxed
poetic about that let's move on to the
world of CrossFit Haley Adams someone
who did not compete in the 2023 CrossFit
Games season took some time off is back
and has announced she's back she
announced she's back via a podcast Phil
give us a rundown if you don't mind of
Haley Adams like who is Haley Adams what
has her competition career been like so
far and why is this a big deal so Haley
Adams has been at the like top end of
the individual women's division since
entering the that division in 2019 after
leaving the uh girls and teens division
so she has multiple 10 finishes with her
highest rank being fourth place in 2020
so in 2019 she ranked sixth in 2020 she
ranked fourth in 2021 she ranked fifth
in 2022 she ranked ninth like this is
consistent Elite performances and she is
dominant in any event that involves
running or like long form endurance like
that's her bread and butter she is cozy
in that space leading up she was one of
Tia clar tumi's like top contenders for
like Tia's dominance during that Reign
before Tia took last year off to have
her first child I was going to say Haley
also you know had a Strong pedigree in
the teen division she got second girls
14 to 15 the next year she got second
girls 16 to 17 then she won first girls
16 to 17 and then she competes as an
individual open right so she in many
ways was seen as the next big thing in
CrossFit for the Women's Division and I
want to clarify her not having a Podium
finisher winning the dang thing yet is
not disappointment she's finished top 10
among the adults in the open division
four years in a row four years in a row
took off 2023 for some personal reasons
we saw a few athletes do that on the
women's side obviously T Clair Tumi gave
birth to her first child um we saw Haley
Adams withdraw to to for some un
relatively
unspecified personal reasons she
mentioned that it was due to to for
mental health purposes but what those
specifically were were not detailed yeah
that is a strange of seven years of
elite competition seven years of the
pressure the Relentless training taking
very few days off and really having to
be dialed in for a very long season and
so I'm personally very happy to see some
of these athletes take Seasons off
because the wear and tear not only on
the body but on the mind of that sort of
elite level stretch I can't even imagine
I mean she grew up in the sport I can't
imagine the sort of mental pressure and
grun that that has been I'm thrilled to
see Haley Adams come back I think she's
a tenacious competitor I'm excited to
see her compete but I also just want to
point out when I heard last year she was
taking time off I was not disappointed
because I can't even imagine how
difficult it is to be at the top of your
game to be competing for the title of
fittest on Earth that many years in a
row I I just can't comprehend it and it
was really interesting too because when
Adams had announced her break in 2023 in
the same year that Tia was taking off
and then also that year was M O'Brien
saying she wasn't she was going to take
the season off and Mal had just come off
of a a runner-up finish and was was also
looked that as potentially the new like
Tia to to to ascend the throne so it's
like you know now it's like you had you
had malban and then uh this past year
you had uh Emma Lawson get us a runner
out finish and now is also looked at as
like oh maybe she's the new you know
dominant thing but then Laura Horvath is
like I've been here this whole time what
do you mean like it's my time now like
I'm going to dominate forever and so
like but at the time before all of these
like young teenagers were just really
dominant in the open feels like Haley
Adams really like set that way for the
younger athletes to come in and do that
in a way where they're like oh this is
doable because Haley Adams was
consistently at the top and she was
consistently at the top while dominant
in certain events like I I will never
forget the 2020 uh CrossFit games where
there's just like this these long runs
these long grindy runs where there's
only five people at the ranch and it
looks like Haley Adams engine just just
never ends she could run forever and
never stop ridiculous engine I'm really
excited for 2024 haly Adams and I think
it adds an interesting wrinkle or Ripple
or component to a very interesting
women's competition where Tia clar Tumi
is coming back from childbirth Laura
horv is the reigning champion and
certainly wants to defend her title you
have a lot of you mentioned Mal O'Brien
like you have a lot of women who are
re-entering competition this year or
maybe re-entering competition we have
some as yet unconfirmed in addition to
all of the women who performed super
well last year like Emma Lawson's a
great example right she's got her eyes
on the podium on the top of the podium
and could very well take it she wore the
leader Jersey for most of the the games
yeah and she's still a teenager she's
still a teenager right like so room room
to grow and improve so I think it's a
really exciting you know I said last
year that Tia Clair Tumi not competing
at the games made it the most exciting
women's division in years I think
actually this year is the most exciting
women's division in years eclipses last
year because T is coming back and
because so many of these athletes are
looking so good and we have some
familiar names returning to the fry
after taking 2023 off for various
reasons well let's talk about someone
who has uh who's looking to add some
Hardware some gold Hardware to the
cabinet that's American Amanda Lawrence
84 kilo powerlifter she has been at the
top of the powerlifting game for a
number of years now I feel like since
barbin was founded back in 2016 Amanda
Lawrence has been on our radar current
world record holder in the squat just
squatted 11 kilos over that in training
she squatted 260 kilos raw which is
about 573 pounds she's an 84 kilogram
woman uh excuse me yeah excuse me excuse
us excuse what what what did we watch
what happened what did she do yeah
that's that's insane her current world
record is 249 kilos so we don't know
what she weighs she might have she it
was likely she's somewhat over body
weight and like that helps on the squat
right heavier P Mass moves Mass so to
speak but she's not that far over body
weight and she didn't do this four
months before the Sheffield she's doing
this about a month before the Sheffield
which is later in February 2024 in the
UK so like I I asked once again excuse
me excuse us excuse me what happened
yeah 11 K like okay yeah maybe if you're
you're chipping at the record or you're
like you know maybe if you're on the
highend you're like okay five kilos with
extra body weight in training you're
breaking some world I mean 11 kilos is
like not close can we expect anything
other than a world record at the
Sheffield from her now I I think what's
interesting too is Amanda Lawrence also
that that squat her 249 that's also
technically the record all time for
tested for the 90 kilo for 90 kilo power
lifters as well which is kind of hilar
is kind of hilarious sorry that's just a
little aside we have had like Jesus
Olivera Tony cliff and now Amanda
Lawrence we've had three weeks in a row
where we've been highlighting these
powerlifters dripping out their training
lists above World Records or in Jesus's
example something close to a world
record for a set of five like they're
just playing with us now I love the
Sheffield all these weight categories
are kind of being pitted to see who puts
up the best total relative to their
division and that's who will ultimately
that's how people walk away with the
biggest cash prizes up to $60,000 us
basically if they if you have a real
darn good day and I love there's just a
little drama because you have all these
different lifters who are like well
here's I'm putting up here's what I'm
putting up and it's a way to kind of
fire a shot across the bow for lifters
who are not even in your weight division
right I mean Amanda Lawrence this might
be the most impressive one she's doing
11 kilos over the world record a month
out that is so far ahead and also Amanda
Lawrence's squats look so good like
squat mechan I just her squat mechanics
are so it's aesthetically look par
thinks out about how you look when you
squat but like her squat mechanics are
aesthetically squatting it's it's like I
I look at that squat I was like wow I I
wish I could do that I just have Envy I
get squat Envy when I look at am mandal
Lauren squat also worth noting she is
the world record holder in the 84 kilo
division in the deadlift 268.50
kilograms I do want to point out Amanda
laen sets that at the Sheffield last
year Natalie La of Australia actually
does exceed that shortly after in local
competition so Amanda still has the
world record but we know there's a
lifter out there in her weight category
in competition Who Has Lifted more off
the ground so I have to imagine Amanda
is looking to exceed her world record in
the deadlift as well not only because
that includes a cash bonus because of
the way Sheffield structured but because
it's a way for her to say like no no no
no I am still the big dog when it comes
to both the squat and deadlift in this
weight class internationally so given
that she's 11 kilos over her squat world
record a month out I can't even begin to
guess what number she's going to call
for on the barbell well let's switch
over to the world of
bodybuilding Chris Bumstead of Canada
the five time five time classic physique
champ arguably the face of modern
bodybuilding would is that fair Phil is
he the modern face of bodybuilding I
mean he's the most popular athlete in
the sport right now he's got the largest
following uh he's in what is arguably
the most popular division at the moment
uh including in Arnold Schwarzenegger's
eyes like yeah I think it's safe to say
that safe to say well Chris bum said two
years in a row he's had injuries leading
up to the Olympia two years in a row he
had a bicep injury and then in 2022 and
then a lat injury in 2023 obviously W in
2023 for phenomenal package he brought
to this stage phenomenal had some life
updates and took some time off of
training now it's not uncommon for
athletes to take some time off training
or to lower the intensity of training
you know after a bodybuilding show Chris
bump said very open about this he went
to Turkey got a hair transplant had to
take a month off from basically any
physical activity any strous activity to
let that heal also announced he's gonna
be a father he's gonna be a dad his
first kid is on the way we can talk a
little bit more about that but while
he's back to training that's Val time
for others in his division to
potentially catch up and there's one big
name that's been nibbling at Chris
bumstead's heels for quite some time
Phil that was uh the first part of an
alleyoop you want to slam it home who is
that ronz has been just right on
bumstead's heels for years at this point
I mean he's gotten multiple runnerup
finishes at the Olympia to to to
bumpstead he has like forearms that sort
of just Boggle the mind of like
how they could be so large
proportionately to a waist you're like
how can your forearms and your waist be
how how does this brain do does not
compute how how do you how do humans
build like this when you compare Ramon
and Chris on stage now Chris is one
Chris Chris is the the five-time champ
right and I don't think anyone's saying
that like he didn't deserve to win in
any of those years right like I
literally don't think anyone's saying
that but it is interesting to see this
extraordinary dominant athlete and if
you look at photos of Chris next to rone
like it is quite easy to see there is a
difference in their forearms now other
parts Chris's back development leg
development things like that abdominal
uh development and conditioning overall
conditioning top tier top tier right
also they recently trained arms together
and I do want to point out the best most
fun rivalries in bodybuilding are when
the athletes like each other I love that
right back to the days of Arnold and
Franco I love a friendly rivalry in
bodybuilding I love when the guys train
together right when they're really
pushing each other I think it's good for
the sport and I think it brings a really
wholesome yet Competitive Edge to
everything in in reality like the the
way that these guys seem to treat the
the the sport is you know they are
competing against themselves you know
they can't necessarily control what the
other guys are doing so they're like
well if I want to be the best I have to
train with the best and so we've seen
Bumstead train with with Ramone we've
seen him train with ERS who's come in
third the you know back toback years
there was actually a moment I forget if
it was this past year or if it was the
year before but there was a moment you
know they were joking on stage they're
very aware that they're one and two you
know on stage together and there was a
point where Bumstead like like
essentially like tapped Ramon's glute or
something while they were standing next
to each other and they were like joking
around on stage because they were you
know just going back and forth as one
and two and uh one the the head judge
was like uh athletes please don't touch
each other on St
it was like you just like stop that
horse play stop that horse play stop
that horse play yeah they they were like
knock out the friendliness this is not a
friendly space this is a competitive
environment Lolly gagging um that was
very funny yeah I also want to say that
Chris Bumstead expecting his first child
with partner Courtney King who is also a
uh former bikini Miss Olympia right so
um you're talking about genetics wishing
them the best we all just want healthy
happy children right but if that kid
comes out with a turtle turtle shell
eight pack I wouldn't be surprised
that's all I'm gonna say that's all I'm
gonna say I'm putting I'm I'm taking the
over under at 12 Olympia wins for baby
Bumstead that is that is the Great
Northern hope for the next generation of
bodybuilding in in 25 years right
because you need some time for you know
mature muscle to really form you need
some time yeah you need some time yeah
yeah and who who knows what classic
physique look like at that point it
looks probably like what Chris bump said
is now CU he seems to be setting just a
new standard for it every year you know
how like old school Arnold was the
standard for classic physique or at
least that was what was referenced right
among fans as like what you should aim
for no one's saying that anymore they're
like no like Bumstead the current champ
is the standard like aim for what he is
doing and that's like the standard for
the division now to see Bumstead sort of
move the trajectory for classic physique
it's interesting to now a will that ever
shift again will the short guys be
actually actually be able to compete
with the tall guys now knowing that okay
Bumstead is at the top but it seems like
verone is ready to like get the hand off
of you know taking over the throne if
and when Bumstead decides to retire or
take a year off because he's becoming a
new father so there's a lot of questions
in the division even though Bumstead
still seems to have the top of it on
lock yeah well Phil that speculation
brings us to the end of this week's
strength leele we'll be back with more
uh probably some more previews leading
up to the Sheffield which will be the
first first massive event in the string
sports calendar this year followed
basically just a week later by the
Arnold where we'll have updates from
across the world of string Sports until
then I'm David Thomas to joined by
what's your name again who are you my
name is Philip and my middle name Edward
Edward bman all right thanks everybody
for joining on strength with e this
[Music]
week